Welcome. If I could have the first slide, please?
مرحبا، إن أمكن أن تظهروا الشريحة الأولى من فضلكم؟
Contrary to calculations made by some engineers, bees can fly,
خلافا للحسابات المجراة من قبل بعض المهندسين، النحل يمكنه الطيران،
dolphins can swim, and geckos can even climb
والدولفين يمكنه السباحة والوزغات يمكنها تسلق
up the smoothest surfaces. Now, what I want to do, in the short time I have,
أكثر الأسطح سلاسة. الآن ما أريد القيام به، في الوقت الضيق المتاح لي،
is to try to allow each of you to experience
هو محاولة إتاحة الفرصة لكل منكم لتجربة،
the thrill of revealing nature's design.
نوعا ما، إثارة الكشف عن تصاميم الطبيعة.
I get to do this all the time, and it's just incredible.
يتاح لي القيام بذلك طوال الوقت، وهو أمر مذهل.
I want to try to share just a little bit of that with you in this presentation.
أريد أن أحاول مشاركة جزء بسيط منه في هذا العرض.
The challenge of looking at nature's designs --
تحدي النظر في تصاميم الطبيعة --
and I'll tell you the way that we perceive it, and the way we've used it.
وسأخبركم عن الطريقة التي نتصوره بها، والطريقة التي استخدمناه لها.
The challenge, of course, is to answer this question:
التحدي بالطبع، هو الجواب عن هذا السؤال:
what permits this extraordinary performance of animals
ما الذي يسمح بهذا الأداء الخارق للحيوانات
that allows them basically to go anywhere?
الذي يسمح لهم أساسا بالذهاب إلى أي مكان؟
And if we could figure that out, how can we implement those designs?
وإن استطعنا معرفة كيف يمكننا تنفيذ تلك التصاميم؟
Well, many biologists will tell engineers, and others,
حسنا، الكثير من علماء الأحياء سيقولون للمهندسين وآخرين،
organisms have millions of years to get it right;
الكائنات الحية أتيحت لها ملايين السنين لتتقنها،
they're spectacular; they can do everything wonderfully well.
إنها مذهلة، تستطيع القيام بأي شيء بغاية الروعة.
So, the answer is bio-mimicry: just copy nature directly.
لذلك الجواب هو تقليد الطبيعة -- فقط نسخ الطبيعة مباشرة.
We know from working on animals that the truth is
نعلم من خلال العمل على الحيوانات أن الحقيقة هي
that's exactly what you don't want to do -- because evolution works
أنه بالضبط ما لا تريد القيام به. لأن التطور يشتغل
on the just-good-enough principle, not on a perfecting principle.
بمبدأ حسن بما فيه الكفاية فقط، ليس بمبدأ المثالية.
And the constraints in building any organism, when you look at it,
والقيود المطروحة في بناء أي كائن حي حين تنظر إليه
are really severe. Natural technologies have incredible constraints.
هي فعلا صارمة. التقانة الطبيعية لها قيود لا تصدق.
Think about it. If you were an engineer and I told you
فكروا في الأمر. إن كنت مهندسا وأخبرتك
that you had to build an automobile, but it had to start off to be this big,
أنه عليك بناء سيارة لكن عليها أن تبدأ بكونها بهذا الحجم،
then it had to grow to be full size and had to work every step along the way.
ثم عليها أن تنموا لتصبح في حجم كامل وعليها ان تبقى تعمل في كل خطوة على الطريق.
Or think about the fact that if you build an automobile, I'll tell you that you also -- inside it --
فكروا في حقيقة أنه إن صنعتم سيارة سأخبركم أنه داخلها
have to put a factory that allows you to make another automobile.
عليكم أن تضعوا مصنعا يتيح إمكانية صناعة سيارة أخرى.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And you can absolutely never, absolutely never, because of history
ولن يمكنكم أبدا، أبدا، بسبب التاريخ
and the inherited plan, start with a clean slate.
والخطة الموروثة، أن تبدؤوا بصفحة بيضاء.
So, organisms have this important history.
وهكذا فإن الكائنات الحية لها هذا التاريخ المهم.
Really evolution works more like a tinkerer than an engineer.
فعلا التطور يشتغل أشبه عامل مبتدئ أكثر من مهندس.
And this is really important when you begin to look at animals.
وهذا بالفعل مهم حين تبدأ في النظر إلى الحيوانات.
Instead, we believe you need to be inspired by biology.
بدلا من ذلك نعتقد أنك تحتاج إلى ان تلهم من طرف علم الأحياء.
You need to discover the general principles of nature,
تحتاج إلى أن تكتشف المبادئ العامة للطبيعة،
and then use these analogies when they're advantageous.
وثم تستخدم هذه القياسات حين تكون مفيدة.
This is a real challenge to do this, because animals,
هذا تحد حقيقي للقيام بالأمر لأن الحيوانات،
when you start to really look inside them -- how they work --
حين تبدأ بالفعل في النظر داخلها، كيف تعيش،
appear hopelessly complex. There's no detailed history
تبدوا معقدة بشكل ميؤوس منه. ليس هناك تاريخ مفصل
of the design plans, you can't go look it up anywhere.
لمخططات التصميم، وليس في إمكانكم أن تذهبوا للبحث عنها في أي مكان.
They have way too many motions for their joints, too many muscles.
لديهم الكثير جدا من الحركات لمفاصلهم، الكثير من العضلات،
Even the simplest animal we think of, something like an insect,
وحتى أبسط حيوان يمكننا التفكير فيه، شيء مثل حشرة،
and they have more neurons and connections than you can imagine.
ولديهم من الخلايا العصبية والروابط أكثر مما يمكنكم تخيله.
How can you make sense of this? Well, we believed --
كيف يمكنك أن تعقلن هذا؟ طيب، نعتقد --
and we hypothesized -- that one way animals could work simply,
ونفترض -- أنه بطريقة واحدة يمكن للحيوانات أن تشتغل ببساطة،
is if the control of their movements
وهي إن كان التحكم في حركاتهم
tended to be built into their bodies themselves.
يميل إلى كونه مدمج في أجسادهم أنفسها.
What we discovered was that two-, four-, six- and eight-legged animals
ما اكتشفناه هو أنه ثنائية ورباعية وسداسية وثمانية الأرجل من الحيوانات
all produce the same forces on the ground when they move.
كلها تطبق نفس القوة على السطح حين تتحرك.
They all work like this kangaroo, they bounce.
كلها تشتغل مثل الكنغر، تقوم بالإرتداد.
And they can be modeled by a spring-mass system that we call the spring mass system
ويمكن أن تنمذج بنظام مخمد الكتلة الذي نسميه نظام مخمد الكتلة
because we're biomechanists. It's actually a pogo stick.
لأننا ميكانيكو أحياء، إنه في الحقيقة عصا القفز.
They all produce the pattern of a pogo stick. How is that true?
كلها تنتج نمط عصا القفز. كيف يكون ذلك صحيحا؟
Well, a human, one of your legs works like two legs of a trotting dog,
طيب، كإنسان، واحدة من رجليك، تشتغل مثل اثنتين عند كلب داب،
or works like three legs, together as one, of a trotting insect,
أو كثلاثة أرجل مجتمعة عند حشرة دابة،
or four legs as one of a trotting crab.
أو أربع أرجل كواحدة عند سلطعون داب.
And then they alternate in their propulsion,
وهكذا يناوبون في الإسناد،
but the patterns are all the same. Almost every organism we've looked at this way
لكن الأنماط هي متشابهة كلها. وتقريبا كل كائن حي نظرنا إليه بهذه الطريقة
-- you'll see next week, I'll give you a hint,
-- سترون في الأسبوع المقبل -- سأعطيكم تلميحا،
there'll be an article coming out that says that really big things
سيكون هناك مقال سيصدر يقول بأن الأشياء الكبيرة بالفعل
like T. rex probably couldn't do this, but you'll see that next week.
مثل T.Rex تستطيع ربما القيام بهذا، لكن سترون في الأسبوع المقبل.
Now, what's interesting is the animals, then -- we said -- bounce along
الآن الذي يهم هو الحيوانات ثم نقول أنها ترتد على طول
the vertical plane this way, and in our collaborations with Pixar,
المستوى العمودي بهذه الطريقة، وفي تعاوننا مع Pixar
in "A Bug's Life," we discussed the
في "حياة حشرة،" تناقشنا حول
bipedal nature of the characters of the ants.
الطبيعة الثنائية القدم لخصائص النمل.
And we told them, of course, they move in another plane as well.
وقلنا لهم بالطبع إنها تتحرك في مستويات أخرى كذلك،
And they asked us this question. They say, "Why model
وطرحوا علينا هذا السؤال. قالو، "لماذا النمذجة
just in the sagittal plane or the vertical plane,
فقط في المستوى العرضي أو المستوى العمودي،
when you're telling us these animals are moving
في حين تخبروننا أن هذه الحيوانات تتحرك
in the horizontal plane?" This is a good question.
في المستوى الأفقي؟" هذا سؤال جيد.
Nobody in biology ever modeled it this way.
لا أحد في علوم الأحياء قام أبدا بالنمذجة بهذه الطريقة.
We took their advice and we modeled the animals moving
أخذنا بنصيحتهم وقمنا بنمذجة الحيوانات تتحرك
in the horizontal plane as well. We took their three legs,
على المستوى الأفقي كذلك. أخذنا أرجلها الثلاثة،
we collapsed them down as one.
جمعناها على أنها واحدة،
We got some of the best mathematicians in the world
جمعنا بعضا من أفضل علماء الرياضيات في العالم
from Princeton to work on this problem.
من جامعة برينستون للعمل على هذا المشكل.
And we were able to create a model
وقد استطعنا أن ننشئ نموذجا
where animals are not only bouncing up and down,
حيث الحيوانات لا ترتد فقط صعودا ونزولا،
but they're also bouncing side to side at the same time.
لكن كذلك عرضيا في نفس الوقت.
And many organisms fit this kind of pattern.
والكثير من الكائنات الحية تناسب هذا النوع من النمط.
Now, why is this important to have this model?
الآن لماذا من المهم الحصول على هذا النموذج؟
Because it's very interesting. When you take this model
لأنه مثير جدا للإهتمام. حين تأخذ هذا النموذج
and you perturb it, you give it a push,
وتشوشه، تعطيه دفعة،
as it bumps into something, it self-stabilizes, with no brain
وهو يرتد نحو شيئ ما، يستقر ذاتيا، بدون دماغ،
or no reflexes, just by the structure alone.
أو ردود فعل، فقط بالبنية وحدها.
It's a beautiful model. Let's look at the mathematics.
إنه نموذج جميل. دعونا ننظر إلى الرياضيات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's enough!
هذا يكفي.
The animals, when you look at them running,
الحيوانات، حين تنظر إليها وهي تجري،
appear to be self-stabilizing like this,
تبدوا وكأنها تستقر ذاتيا هكذا،
using basically springy legs. That is, the legs can do
باستعمال أرجل زنبركية أساسا. هذا يعني، الرجل يمكنها أن تنجز
computations on their own; the control algorithms, in a sense,
خوارزمية التحكم بمعنى ما
are embedded in the form of the animal itself.
مدمجة في شكل الحيوان نفسه.
Why haven't we been more inspired by nature and these kinds of discoveries?
لماذا لم نكن أكثر إلهاما من الطبيعة وهذا النوع من الإكتشافات؟
Well, I would argue that human technologies are really different from
حسنا، أنا أزعم أن التقانات الإنسانية هي فعلا مختلفة عن
natural technologies, at least they have been so far.
التقانات الطبيعية، على الأقل كانت كذلك لحد الآن.
Think about the typical kind of robot that you see.
فكروا في النوع القياسي للإنسان الآلي الذي ترونه.
Human technologies have tended to be large, flat,
التقانات الإنسانية تميل إلى كونها كبيرة ومسطحة،
with right angles, stiff, made of metal. They have rolling devices
مع زوايا سوية وصلبة ومصنوعة من المعدن. مع أجهزة زالجة
and axles. There are very few motors, very few sensors.
ومحاور. هناك عدد قليل جدا من المحركات، عدد قليل جدا من أجهزة الإستشعار.
Whereas nature tends to be small, and curved,
في حين الطبيعة تميل إلى كونها صغيرة، متقوسة،
and it bends and twists, and has legs instead, and appendages,
وتنحني وتبرم ولها أرجل بدلا عن الزوائد،
and has many muscles and many, many sensors.
ولديها الكثير من العضلات والكثير، الكثير من أجهزة الإستشعار.
So it's a very different design. However, what's changing,
وهكذا فهو تصميم مختلف جدا. ومع ذلك، ما يتغير،
what's really exciting -- and I'll show you some of that next --
ما يثير بالفعل -- وسأريكم بعضا من ذلك لاحقا --
is that as human technology takes on more of the characteristics
هو أنه كما أن التقانة الإنسانية تأخذ على أكثر من خصائص
of nature, then nature really can become a much more useful teacher.
الطبيعة، آنذاك الطبيعة بالفعل يمكنها أن تصبح معلمة أكثر نفعا بكثير.
And here's one example that's really exciting.
وهنا مثال مثير حقا.
This is a collaboration we have with Stanford.
هذا تعاون لدينا مع ستانفورد.
And they developed this new technique, called Shape Deposition Manufacturing.
وقد طوروا هذه التقنية الجديدة أسموها تصنيع شكل الترسيب.
It's a technique where they can mix materials together and mold any shape
إنها تقنية حيث يمكن أن تخلط المواد مع بعضها وتقولب أي شكل
that they like, and put in the material properties.
يريدونه، وتضع خصائص المادة.
They can embed sensors and actuators right in the form itself.
يستطيعون دمج أجهزة استشعار ومحركات على الشكل نفسه.
For example, here's a leg: the clear part is stiff,
على سبيل المثال، هنا رجل -- الجزء الواضح صلب،
the white part is compliant, and you don't need any axles there or anything.
الجزء الأبيض متوافق، ولا تحتاج أي محاور هناك أو أي شيء.
It just bends by itself beautifully.
تنحني فقط لذاتها بشكل جميل.
So, you can put those properties in. It inspired them to show off
إذاً يمكن أن تضع تلك الخواص فيها. ألهمتهم أن يتباهوا
this design by producing a little robot they named Sprawl.
بهذا التصميم بإنتاج روبوت صغير أسموه Sprawl.
Our work has also inspired another robot, a biologically inspired bouncing robot,
عملنا قد ألهم كذلك روبوتا آخر، روبوت ارتداد ملهم أحيائيا،
from the University of Michigan and McGill
من جامعة ميتشيغان وماكغيل
named RHex, for robot hexapod, and this one's autonomous.
سمي RHex، والتي تعني روبوت سداسي الأرجل، وهذا مستقل بذاته.
Let's go to the video, and let me show you some of these animals moving
دعنا نذهب إلى الفيديو ودعوني أريكم بعض هذه الحيوانات تتحرك.
and then some of the simple robots
ثم بعض الروبوتات البسيطة
that have been inspired by our discoveries.
التي ألهمتها اكتشافاتنا.
Here's what some of you did this morning, although you did it outside,
هذا ما قام به بعضكم هذا الصباح، مع أنكم قمتم به خارجا
not on a treadmill.
ليس في جهاز جري.
Here's what we do.
هذا ما نفعله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is a death's head cockroach. This is an American cockroach
هذا صرصور من نوع (death's head) -- هذا صرصور أمريكي
you think you don't have in your kitchen.
والذي تعتقدون أنكم لا يوجد في مطبخكم.
This is an eight-legged scorpion, six-legged ant, forty-four-legged centipede.
هذا عقرب ثماني الأرجل، نملة سداسية الأرجل، أم أربعة وأربعين.
Now, I said all these animals are sort of working like pogo sticks --
الآن قلت أن كل هذه الحيوانات تعمل نوعا ما كعصي قفز --
they're bouncing along as they move. And you can see that
إنها ترتد على طول وهي تتحرك ويمكنكم رؤية ذلك
in this ghost crab, from the beaches of Panama and North Carolina.
وفي حالة هذا السلطعون الشبح من شواطئ بناما ونورث كارولينا.
It goes up to four meters per second when it runs.
تصل إلى أربعة أمتار في الثانية حين يجري.
It actually leaps into the air, and has aerial phases
هو في الحقيقة يقفز في الهواء ولديه أطوار جوية
when it does it, like a horse, and you'll see it's bouncing here.
حين يقوم بذلك، كحصان، وسترونه يرتد هنا.
What we discovered is whether you look at the leg of a human
الذي اكتشفناه هو أنه سواء نظرت إلى رجل إنسان
like Richard, or a cockroach, or a crab, or a kangaroo,
مثل ريتشارد، أو صرصور، أو سلطعون أو كنغر،
the relative leg stiffness of that spring is the same for everything we've seen so far.
صلابة الرجل النسبية لهذا النابض هي نفسها لكل ما قد رأيناه لحد الآن.
Now, what good are springy legs then? What can they do?
الآن ما الجيد في الأرجل النابضة إذاً، ما الذي يمكنها القيام به؟
Well, we wanted to see if they allowed the animals
حسنا، أردنا أن نرى إن كانت تسمح لهذه الحيوانات
to have greater stability and maneuverability.
أن تكون لها ثباتا وقدرة مناورة أعظم.
So, we built a terrain that had obstacles three times the hip height
وبالتالي أنشأنا بقعة فيها عوائق أكثر ارتفاعا بثلاثة مرات من ارتفاع ورك
of the animals that we're looking at.
الحيوانات التي نراها،
And we were certain they couldn't do this. And here's what they did.
وكنا متأكدين أنها لن تستطيع القيام بهذا. وهذا ما قاموا به.
The animal ran over it and it didn't even slow down!
الحيوان دهسها ولم يبطئ حتى.
It didn't decrease its preferred speed at all.
لم يخفض من سرعته المفضلة على الإطلاق.
We couldn't believe that it could do this. It said to us
لم نستطيع أن نصدق أنه بإمكانه القيام بذلك. قد قالت لنا
that if you could build a robot with very simple, springy legs,
أنه إن أمكنك أن تصنع روبوتا بأرجل نابضية بسيطة،
you could make it as maneuverable as any that's ever been built.
يمكنك أن تجعله قادرا على المناورة أكثر من أي روبوت تم إنشاؤه.
Here's the first example of that. This is the Stanford
هنا أول مثال على ذلك، هذا روبوت
Shape Deposition Manufactured robot, named Sprawl.
مصنع بطريقة ترسيب الشكل من ستانفورد سمي Sprawl.
It has six legs -- there are the tuned, springy legs.
لديه ستة أرجل -- هنا الأرجل النابضة المضبوطة.
It moves in a gait that an insect uses, and here it is
تتحرك بمشية الحشرة وها هي هنا
going on the treadmill. Now, what's important about this robot,
تتحرك في آلة الجري. الآن المهم حول هذا الروبوت،
compared to other robots, is that it can't see anything,
بالمقارنة مع الروبوتات الأخرى، هو أنه لا يمكنه رؤية أي شيء،
it can't feel anything, it doesn't have a brain, yet it can maneuver
لا يمكنه الشعور بأي شيء، ليس لديه دماغ، ومع ذلك يمكنه أن يناور
over these obstacles without any difficulty whatsoever.
فوق هذه العوائق بدون أي صعوبة تذكر.
It's this technique of building the properties into the form.
إنها تقنية إنشاء الخصائص في الشكل هذه.
This is a graduate student. This is what he's doing to his thesis project --
هذا طالب دراسات عليا، هذا ما يقوم به في مشروع أطروحته،
very robust, if a graduate student
شاق جدا إن طالب دراسات عليا
does that to his thesis project.
قام بهذا كمشروع أطروحته.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is from McGill and University of Michigan. This is the RHex,
هذا من ماكغيل وجامعة ميتشيغان، هذا هو الRHex،
making its first outing in a demo.
يقوم بأول خرجة له كعرض.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Same principle: it only has six moving parts,
نفس المبدأ. يمتلك فقط ستة أجزاء متحركة.
six motors, but it has springy, tuned legs. It moves in the gait of the insect.
ستة محركات، لكنه يتوفر على أرجل نابضية ومضبطة. يتحرك في مشية الحشرة
It has the middle leg moving in synchrony with the front,
الرجل الوسطى لديه تتحرك في تزامن مع الواجهة
and the hind leg on the other side. Sort of an alternating tripod,
والرجل الخلفية في الجهة الأخرى. نوع من ثلاثي أرجل تناوبي،
and they can negotiate obstacles just like the animal.
وتستطيع التغلب على العوائق تماما كالحيوان.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Voice: Oh my God.)
يا إلهي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Robert Full: It'll go on different surfaces -- here's sand --
سيذهب في أسطح مختلفة، هنا الرمل،
although we haven't perfected the feet yet, but I'll talk about that later.
على الرغم من أننا لم نقم بإتمام القدم بعد، لكن سأتحدث عن ذلك لاحقا.
Here's RHex entering the woods.
هنا RHex يدخل الغابة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Again, this robot can't see anything, it can't feel anything,
مجددا هذا الروبوت لا يستطيع رؤية أي شيء، لا يستطيع الشعور بأي شيء،
it has no brain. It's just working with a tuned mechanical system,
ليس لديه دماغ. يشتغل فقط عن طريق نظام ميكانيكي مضبوط،
with very simple parts, but inspired from the fundamental dynamics of the animal.
بأجزاء بسيطة جدا. لكن ملهمة من أساسيات دينامية الحيوان.
(Voice: Ah, I love him, Bob.) RF: Here's it going down a pathway.
أوه، إني أحبه يا بوب. هاهو هنا يسير نزولا في طريق.
I presented this to the jet propulsion lab at NASA, and they said
قمت بعرض هذا على مختبر الدفع النفاث في NASA، وقالوا
that they had no ability to go down craters to look for ice,
أنهم ليست لديهم أي قدرة على الذهاب نزولا في الحفر للبحث عن الثلج،
and life, ultimately, on Mars. And he said --
والحياة أساسا، في المريخ. وقال --
especially with legged-robots, because they're way too complicated.
خصوصا مع الروبوت ذي الأرجل لأنها معقدة جدا.
Nothing can do that. And I talk next. I showed them this video
لا شيء يمكنه القيام بذلك. وتحدثت لاحقا. أريتهم هذا الفيديو
with the simple design of RHex here. And just to convince them
بهذا التصميم البسيط ل RHex هنا، وفقط لإقناعهم
we should go to Mars in 2011, I tinted the video orange
بأنه علينا الذهاب إلى المريخ في 2011، لونت الفيديو بالبرتقالي
just to give them the sense of being on Mars.
فقط لإعطائهم معنى الوجود في المريخ.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Another reason why animals have extraordinary performance,
سبب آخر لماذا الحيوانات لديها أداء خارق
and can go anywhere, is because they have an effective interaction
ويمكنها الذهاب إلى أي مكان، هو أنها لديها تفاعل ناجح
with the environment. The animal I'm going to show you,
مع المحيط. الحيوان الذي سأريكم إياه
that we studied to look at this, is the gecko.
الذي درسناه للنظر في الأمر هو الوزغة.
We have one here and notice its position. It's holding on.
لدينا واحد هنا ولاحظوا موضعه. إنه متمسك.
Now I'm going to challenge you. I'm going show you a video.
الآن سأتحداكم. سأريكم فيديو.
One of the animals is going to be running on the level,
أحد الحيوانات سيقوم بالجري في المستوى،
and the other one's going to be running up a wall. Which one's which?
وآخر يجري صعودا على الجدار. أيهما أي واحد؟
They're going at a meter a second. How many think the one on the left
تتحرك بمتر في الثانية. كم منكم يظن أن الذي على اليسار
is running up the wall?
يجري صعودا على الجدار؟
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Okay. The point is it's really hard to tell, isn't it? It's incredible,
حسنا. الغرض هو أنه فعلا يصعب التفريق، أليس كذلك؟ أمر لا يصدق،
we looked at students do this and they couldn't tell.
أملنا أن يقوم الطلبة بالقيام بذلك ولم يستطيعوا.
They can run up a wall at a meter a second, 15 steps per second,
تستطيع الجري صعودا في الجدار بسرعة متر في الثانية، 15 خطوة في الثانية
and they look like they're running on the level. How do they do this?
وتبدوا كأنها تجري على المستوى. كيف تقوم بذلك؟
It's just phenomenal. The one on the right was going up the hill.
إنه أمر استثنائي. الذي على اليمين كان يجري صعودا في التل.
How do they do this? They have bizarre toes. They have toes
كيف يمكنها القيام بذلك -- لديها أصابع قدم عجيبة -- لديها أصابع قدم
that uncurl like party favors when you blow them out,
تنسدل مثل بالونات الحفل حين تنفخها،
and then peel off the surface, like tape.
ثم تقشر السطح كشريط لاصق.
Like if we had a piece of tape now, we'd peel it this way.
وكأنه لدينا قطعة من شريط لاصق وقشرناه الآن بهذه الطريقة.
They do this with their toes. It's bizarre! This peeling inspired
يفعلون ذلك بأصابع أقدامهم. إنه عجيب. هذا التقشير ألهم
iRobot -- that we work with -- to build Mecho-Geckos.
iRobot التي نشتغل معها، لإنشاء Mecho-Geckos.
Here's a legged version and a tractor version, or a bulldozer version.
هنا نسخة بالأرجل ونسخة الجرارة أو نسخة الجرافة.
Let's see some of the geckos move with some video,
دعونا نرى بعض الوزغات تتحرك في الفيديو،
and then I'll show you a little bit of a clip of the robots.
ثم سأريكم مقطعا قصيرا للروبوتات.
Here's the gecko running up a vertical surface. There it goes,
هنا الوزغة تجري صعودا في سطح عمودي، هاهي تتحرك،
in real time. There it goes again. Obviously, we have to slow this down a little bit.
بالوقت الفعلي، هنا تتحرك مجددا. من الواضح أنه علينا أن نبطئ هذا قليلا.
You can't use regular cameras.
لا تستطيعون استخدام كامرات عادية.
You have to take 1,000 pictures per second to see this.
يجب أن تأخذوا 1,000 صورة في الثانية لرؤية هذا.
And here's some video at 1,000 frames per second.
وهنا فيديو ب1,000 صورة في الثانية.
Now, I want you to look at the animal's back.
الآن أريدكم أن تنظروا إلى ظهر الحيوان.
Do you see how much it's bending like that? We can't figure that out --
هل ترون كم يتقوس كهذا؟ لا نستطيع استيعاب ذلك --
that's an unsolved mystery. We don't know how it works.
ذاك غموض لم يحل. لا نعرف كيف يشتغل.
If you have a son or a daughter that wants to come to Berkeley,
إن كان لديكم ابن أو بنت يريد أن يأتي إلى بيركيلي،
come to my lab and we'll figure this out. Okay, send them to Berkeley
تعالوا إلى مختبري وسنستوعبه معا. حسنا، أرسلوهم إلى بيركيلي
because that's the next thing I want to do. Here's the gecko mill.
لأنه ذاك هو ثاني شيء أريد القيام به. هنا مصنع الوزغات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a see-through treadmill with a see-through treadmill belt,
هذه رؤية من خلال جهاز جري بحزام يسمح بالرؤية من خلاله،
so we can watch the animal's feet, and videotape them
ليمكننا مشاهدة أقدام الحيوانات، والفيديو يصورهم
through the treadmill belt, to see how they move.
من خلال حزام جهاز الجري، لرؤية كيف تتحرك.
Here's the animal that we have here, running on a vertical surface.
هنا الحيوان الذي لدينا هنا، يجري في مستوى عمودي،
Pick a foot and try to watch a toe, and see if you can see what the animal's doing.
اختاروا قدما وحاولوا مشاهدة أصبع، وانظروا إن أمكنكم رؤية ما يقوم به الحيوان.
See it uncurl and then peel these toes.
سترون أنه يسدل ثم يقشر تلك الأصابع.
It can do this in 14 milliseconds. It's unbelievable.
تستطيع القيام بذلك في 14 ميلي ثانية. إنه أمر لا يصدق.
Here are the robots that they inspire, the Mecho-Geckos from iRobot.
هنا الروبوتات التي ألهمت، ال Mecho-Geckos من طرف iRobot.
First we'll see the animals toes peeling -- look at that.
أولا سنرى أصابع قدم الحيوانات تقشر -- أنظروا إلى ذلك.
And here's the peeling action of the Mecho-Gecko.
وهنا حركة التقشير في ال Mecho-Gecko
It uses a pressure-sensitive adhesive to do it.
تستخدم لاصقا حساسا للضغط للقيام بذلك.
Peeling in the animal. Peeling in the Mecho-Gecko --
التقشير في الحيوان، والتقشير في الMecho-Gecko،
that allows them climb autonomously. Can go on the flat surface,
ذلك يتيح لهم تسلقا مستقلا قد يكون في الأسطح المستوية
transition to a wall, and then go onto a ceiling.
الإنتقال إلى جدار، ثم التحرك على السقف.
There's the bulldozer version. Now, it doesn't use pressure-sensitive glue.
تلك نسخة الجرافة. الآن لا تستخدم اللصاق الحساس للضغط.
The animal does not use that.
الحيوان لا يستخدم ذلك.
But that's what we're limited to, at the moment.
لكن هذا ما نحن مقيدون به الآن.
What does the animal do? The animal has weird toes.
ما الذي يقوم به الحيوان؟ الحيوان له أصابع قدم غريبة،
And if you look at the toes, they have these little leaves there,
وإن نظرنا إلى أصابع القدم لديها أوراق صغيرة هناك،
and if you blow them up and zoom in, you'll see
وإن نفخت فيها وقربت الصورة سترى
that's there's little striations in these leaves.
أن هناك تصدعات صغيرة في هذه الأوراق.
And if you zoom in 270 times, you'll see it looks like a rug.
وإن قربت 270 مرة، سترى أنها تبدوا مثل بساط.
And if you blow that up, and zoom in 900 times,
وإن نفختها، وقربت الصورة ب900 مرة،
you see there are hairs there, tiny hairs. And if you look carefully,
ترى أن هناك شعيرات، شعيرات دقيقة، وإن نظرت بإمعان
those tiny hairs have striations. And if you zoom in on those 30,000 times,
تلك الشعيرات الدقيقة لديها تصدعات. وإن قربت الصورة ب30,000 مرة،
you'll see each hair has split ends.
سترى أن لكل شعيرة نهاية متصدعة.
And if you blow those up, they have these little structures on the end.
وإن نفخت أولئك لديهم تلك البنيات الصغيرة في النهاية.
The smallest branch of the hairs looks like spatulae,
أصغر فروع هذه الشعيرات يبدو مثل ملعقة الصيدلي
and an animal like that has one billion of these nano-size split ends,
وحيوان كهذا لديه مليار من هذه النهايات المتصدعة النانوية الحجم
to get very close to the surface. In fact, there's the diameter of your hair --
لكي يقترب بقدر الإمكان من السطح. في الحقيقة هذا قطر شعركم،
a gecko has two million of these, and each hair has 100 to 1,000 split ends.
الوزغة لديها مليونان من تلك وفي كل شعيرة 100 إلى 1,000 نهاية متصدعة.
Think of the contact of that that's possible.
فكروا في حجم التلامس الممكن هنا.
We were fortunate to work with another group
كنا محظوظين للعمل مع مجموعة أخرى
at Stanford that built us a special manned sensor,
في ستانفورد والتي أنشأت لنا استشعار مأهولية خاص
that we were able to measure the force of an individual hair.
بحيث كنا قادرين على قياس قوة شعيرة منفردة.
Here's an individual hair with a little split end there.
هنا شعيرة منفردة مع نهاية متصدعة هناك،
When we measured the forces, they were enormous.
حين قمنا بقياس القوى كانت هائلة،
They were so large that a patch of hairs about this size --
كانت في غاية القوة بحيث أن جزء من الشعيرات بحوالي هذا الحجم،
the gecko's foot could support the weight of a small child,
قدم الوزغة تستطيع تحمل وزن طفل صغير --
about 40 pounds, easily. Now, how do they do it?
حوالي 40 رطلا بسهولة. الآن كيف تقوم بذلك؟
We've recently discovered this. Do they do it by friction?
قمنا مؤخرا باكتشاف ذلك. هل تقوم بذلك عن طريق الإحتكاك؟
No, force is too low. Do they do it by electrostatics?
لا، القوة ضعيفة جدا. هل تقوم بذلك عن طريق الكهرباء الساكنة؟
No, you can change the charge -- they still hold on.
لا، يمكن أن تغير الشحنة، وتبقى متمسكة.
Do they do it by interlocking? That's kind of a like a Velcro-like thing.
هل يقومون بذلك عن طريق المشابكة؟ ذاك نوع من لصاقات فيلكرو.
No, you can put them on molecular smooth surfaces -- they don't do it.
لا، يمكنك وضعها في سطح أملس جزيئيا -- لا يقومون بذلك.
How about suction? They stick on in a vacuum.
ماذا عن الرشف؟ يستطيعون الإلتصاق في الفراغ.
How about wet adhesion? Or capillary adhesion?
ماذا عن الإلتحام؟ أو الإلتحام الرفيع؟
They don't have any glue, and they even stick under water just fine.
ليست لديهم أي لصاق وقد التصقت تحت الماء حتى بشكل ممتاز.
If you put their foot under water, they grab on.
إن وضعت قدمها تحت الماء تبقى ممسكة.
How do they do it then? Believe it or not, they grab on
كيف تقوم بذلك إذاً؟ صدق أو لا تصدق تستطيع التمسك
by intermolecular forces, by Van der Waals forces.
عن طريق قوى الجزيئات ، قوى فان دير فال.
You know, you probably had this a long time ago in chemistry,
تعلمون أنكم غالبا قد درستم هذا قبل مدة طويلة في الكيمياء
where you had these two atoms, they're close together,
حين كانت لديكم تلك الذرتان، تكون قريبة لبعضها،
and the electrons are moving around. That tiny force is sufficient
والألكترونات تتحرك. تلك القوة الدقيقة كافية
to allow them to do that because it's added up so many times
للسماح لها بالقيام بذلك لأنها تتجمع مرات كثيرة
with these small structures.
مع تلك البنيات الصغيرة.
What we're doing is, we're taking that inspiration of the hairs,
الذي سنقوم به هو أخذ ذلك الإلهام المستوحى من الشعيرات،
and with another colleague at Berkeley, we're manufacturing them.
ومع زميل آخر في بيركيلي، نقوم بتصنيعهم.
And just recently we've made a breakthrough, where we now believe
ومؤخرا فقط قد وصلنا إلى تقدم معرفي مفاجئ يجعلنا نعتقد
we're going to be able to create the first synthetic, self-cleaning,
أننا سنكون قادرين على إنشاء أول لحام جاف اصطناعي
dry adhesive. Many companies are interested in this.
وينظف ذاتيا. العديد من الشركات مهتمة بهذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We also presented to Nike even.
وقد عرضناه لNike حتى.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We'll see where this goes. We were so excited about this
سنرى إلى أين يذهب هذا. كنا جد متحمسين حول هذا
that we realized that that small-size scale --
أن أدركنا أن ذلك المستوى ذي الحجم الصغير،
and where everything gets sticky, and gravity doesn't matter anymore --
وحيث كل شيء يصبح لزجا، والجاذبية لا تهم بعد ذلك،
we needed to look at ants and their feet, because
احتجنا إلى النظر إلى النمل وأقدامها، لأن
one of my other colleagues at Berkeley has built a six-millimeter silicone
أحد زملائي في بيركيلي، قد صنع روبوتا سيليكونيا
robot with legs. But it gets stuck. It doesn't move very well.
من ستة ميليمترات بأرجل. لكنها تلتصق. لا تتحرك بشكل جيد.
But the ants do, and we'll figure out why, so that ultimately
لكن النمل يفعل وسنكتشف لماذا، بحيث أنه في النهاية
we'll make this move. And imagine: you're going to be able
سنقوم بهذه الحركة. وتخيلوا، ستكونون قادرين على
to have swarms of these six-millimeter robots available to run around.
جعل أسراب من روبوتات من ستة ميليمترات متوافرة للف والدوران.
Where's this going? I think you can see it already.
إلى أين يصل هذا؟ أظن أنه يمكنكم رؤيته بالفعل.
Clearly, the Internet is already having eyes and ears,
من الواضح أن الأنترنيت لها بالفعل آذان وعيون،
you have web cams and so forth. But it's going to also have legs and hands.
لديكم كامرات ويب وهكذا دواليك. لكنه سيتوفر كذلك على أرجل وأيدي.
You're going to be able to do programmable
ستكونون قادرين على القيام بعمل قابل
work through these kinds of robots, so that you can run,
للبرمجة عن طريق هذا النوع من الروبوتات، بحيث يمكنك الجري،
fly and swim anywhere. We saw David Kelly is at the beginning of that with his fish.
الطيران والسباحة في كل مكان. رأينا في بداية ذلك دايفيد كيلي مع سمكته.
So, in conclusion, I think the message is clear.
إذاً في الختام ، أظن أن الرسالة واضحة.
If you need a message, if nature's not enough, if you care about
إن كنتم بحاجة إلى رسالة، إن كانت الطبيعة غير كافية، إن كنتم تهتمون ب
search and rescue, or mine clearance, or medicine,
البحث والإنقاذ، أو نزع الألغام، أو الطب،
or the various things we're working on, we must preserve
أو الأمور المتنوعة التي نشتغل عليها، يجب علينا أن نحافظ على
nature's designs, otherwise these secrets will be lost forever.
تصاميم الطبيعة، وإلا هذه الأسرار ستفقد إلى الأبد.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)